So today we're going to talk about
inference scaling. Um we briefly hinted
on this uh in the first lecture. So
there are three stages for LLM kind of
development. The first one is
pre-training. This stage historically
takes a lot more time. It could take
several months. a whole lot of uh GPUs
uh that are used for training these. Um
and then there's a fine-tuning step.
Usually this is a less or historically
has been a less kind of compute intense
process. If you're talking about
trillions of uh data tokens in the
pre-training side on the fine-tuning
side, this is orders of magnitude less
data that we use for fine-tuning. And
then there is the inference part where
we get to use the model and uh we are
going to see different ways that at
inference time we can make the model be
better and become more useful without
changing uh the parameters of the model
and without any kind of uh fine-tuning
of the models.
So uh let's first start with the large
language monkeys paper. Again, uh you
are familiar with the infinite monkey
theorem by now because we discussed it
on uh uh Monday. But to recap, the idea
of this paper is that we have an LLM and
we have a problem as input. Instead of
generating the response for this problem
only once, we are going to repeatedly
ask the same input problem again and
again. Uh this could be a number of
times, it could be 10 times, 100 times
and so on. uh and we will see how that
affects the performance and then we are
going to have a verifier that can tell
us which one of these responses were the
correct response
and then that is going to be the output
of this system.
The reason we like that is that by doing
this repeated sampling, we can make
models that are inferior. For example, a
llama 38B or 7P that is um not as
capable at GPT40 with single attempt. By
by doing this repeated sampling and
selecting the correct one among the
generated
candidates, we can um significantly
improve the performance of these
inferior models and make them better
than these uh larger and proprietary
ones. And these are here you can see
examples across uh really hard math
coding uh uh and different styles of
math problem uh question answering
problems.
Is that is this clear to everyone? Um it
just seems like the models and smaller
models already know the answers to these
hard problems and we are just like by
doing this repeated sampling we are kind
of eliciting those and surfacing those
answers.
It just they don't and they they just
don't tell us that in the first trial.
Um now this um
uh kind of paradigm of repeated sampling
works well across pretty much any domain
that we have tried in so far including
agentic uh benchmarks such as bbench
which kind of mimics like how a software
engineer goes about um editing code and
creating new patches. Um so here we are
seeing the coverage meaning uh the the
the uh fraction of problems that are
solved by at least one of the samples
and here on the x-axis we have the
number of samples going from one to a
thousand and what we are seeing here is
that a model such as deepseek um
can u uh I I believe this was the
deepseek v3 model can perform can
outperform models such as claw 3.5 or 01
uh preview um after a thousand samples
like it can solve more coding and
software engineering problems than those
and the reason this is interesting is
that we are doing um uh in this case for
coding problems if we have unit tests
that can that we can use to select which
one of these samples is correct then we
have an end toend automated way to
create a more capable model um out of
this in this case out of Deepseek and
open source model.
Um now again we saw pre-training scaling
laws in the last class uh and that was
we can predictably
uh kind of reduce the test loss given
these equations in in this paper and
these equations might might change given
the setup but there is a predictable
path to increase data uh amount of
compute used and the number of
parameters in the model and use that uh
to kind of uh predict or reduce the test
loss. So this is for pre-training but it
turns out we can define a similar
scaling loss but this time for inference
or test time compute. Um and that is
something that we showed in this paper.
Basically you're showing that the
relationship between co coverage and the
number of samples that are being drawn
in parallel from the model follow an
exponential power law. So assume this C
is coverage meaning how many problems
are solved by at least one of the
samples and then K is the number of
samples and A and B are these kind of
coefficient that we can find through
this uh the carefidding parameters that
we can find through this scaling uh kind
of u uh scaling behavior of the model.
So concretely um as we scaled the number
of samples across a range of models from
llama 3 8b 7eb and models like gemma or
pithia uh and this is for various range
of parameter sizes going from 70 million
parameter parameters all the way to 70
billion parameters. We can see that we
can u predict this power law and have a
have a have a predicted curve that um
closely for for the most part very
closely follows the actual u practical
kind of coverage that we are seeing as
we increase the number of samples. So
basically the way to think about it is
that we can we can predict how many
sample to achieve a certain coverage how
many samples we're going to need to and
and how much we should how much
resources we should allocate to achieve
that.
Um and again the these curves show that
this behavior is true for a range of
models and a range of parameter sizes.
Again I think one of the very
interesting properties that we saw here
is that for a very small model like a 70
million parameter we also see this
scaling behavior and of course this is
true for much larger models as well and
it is true across domains.
Now, uh we uh we looked a bit more into
why we see this um kind of paral law
behavior in in in repeated sample
sampling. um because it's it might be at
first a little non-intuitive because if
the probability of um
the pass atmon being correct the
probability of a correct response to a
to a question is for example P then we
can calculate the probability of um at
least one of the answers being correct
at K for an individual problems. So for
problem I, if we have the pass at one
for problem I, we can calculate directly
what is pass at K for problem I with
this um exponential equation. I hope
this is clear for everybody. But
basically this 1 minus P is the
probability of the first like K answers
not being correct and then one minus
that is the probability of at least one
of these K answers being correct. So
this is for an individual problem.
But what we are seeing that across a
suite of problems we are seeing the
expon the power law uh scaling law
meaning across um AC across these
problems we are seeing the the the
equations are changing. So the question
that we wanted to answer is that how
does this what kind of behavior should
we see across uh the problem examples in
a data set that justifies our
exponential um uh sorry our power loss
scaling loss. Um and by looking into
that further um uh what uh what was
observed is that in order to have the
scaling laws that we observed there has
to be the sufficient and necessary
condition for it is that we have a long
tail of hard problems.
Um
basically from a ma mathematical
perspective we are going to need that
because this is the the power law
scaling. This is the per problem uh
exponential scaling laws and this is
like this kind of these sort we need to
have these sort of cur curve for the
pass at one of problems in order to
justify this um uh power loss scaling.
And empirically when we looked into the
problems we saw that this condition
holds. And again what this condition is
is that we have a long tail uh of really
hard hard problems on the most on the
most complex side of things. For
example, um let's take a look at this
model and and the count of uh the count
of problems that are solved at passad
one and uh at more and more samples. It
seems like across all these problems, a
large portion of problems are simpler
and they're solved in pass one. And as
we increase the complexity of the
problems uh where the pass one
probability is going to become lower and
lower we have like a long pair of
problems that kind of have that
property.
So these kind of curve that you see here
from high at simpler problems and low at
harder and harder problems meaning lower
and lower pass at one is the type of
problems is the type of behavior that we
are seeing across these uh task and that
is why uh we can see the the scaling
loss that we that that we have that we
have observed.
Now
um
what this means for
the the science and the engineering
around LLMs is that while previously
companies would would spend hundreds of
millions of dollars or billion of dollar
uh billions of dollar on pre-training
alone and then a lot less on fine-tuning
and then almost like nothing at each
inference call because it used to be
like a on time back and forth between
the user and query and the model. Now we
have a new paradigm where we can spend a
whole lot more compute on inference and
use that to increase the capability of
model and this compute the inference
compute can be done offline. We can kind
of uh release our agents to go solve a
problem and just keep generating tokens
and keep uh improving the the the
quality of the answers that they
generate.
Um now when we talk about this repeated
sampling something that that's important
to
kind of have in mind is the need for
automated verification because if you
have a bunch of samples we still need to
know which one of them are the correct
ones and how to go about selecting them.
um
in certain domains uh verification is
easier than the others. For example, for
certain types of math problems, you can
use formal formal proofs. So given a a
proof u strategy, we can run them by
these formal proof kind of software
tools to verify whether each step is
correct or not. Um we can write unit
tests for coding and um in some cases
writing a unit test arguably arguably is
a much simpler task than writing the
entire program that solves a problem.
Right? So the unit test can be written
for example by humans um and um we can
use that as our verifier.
Um there are other cases like AI as a
compiler and this is one of the projects
in the lab. um that and a direction that
I'm very excited about and that is when
we can generate compiler like lower
level code like CUDA for a source code
like P pietorch with LLM and the reason
this is verifiable is that um for
example here we can always
um compare the output of CUDA with the
source PyTorch and see if they're the
same for for any given input. Right? So
we don't need if we want to say whether
the model has generate has generated the
correct CUDA code for our source PyTorch
code we can just see um whether their
outputs match for any for any inputs.
Um
for those of you who are not familiar
for CUDA, I hope you you all are, but
it's like a lower level language for
writing uh more hardware aware and
optimized for hardware code uh for on on
GPUs.
Um for example, here um we we have a
data set or a benchmark on CUDA
generation called kernel bench. And here
again we are seeing the same s sort of
uh linear improving coverage uh in this
case for CUDA code generation as we
increase the number of samples that we
take from the model. And in this case we
have this again by by default perfect
verifier that we can use for um
measuring the correctness of our CUDA
generated code.
And and there are other examples of this
um other any basically any kind of
translation between two languages. If
you want to like port from Python or C++
to Java or vice versa. This is again
this is true. You can measure the the
equivalency
uh much easier. Um now there are domains
that we don't have verifier for and in
those domains what we observe was that
there is a large gap between best of end
methods uh such as majority v voting um
and uh and model based rankers and what
is the true coverage of the model. Let's
take a look at one example here. Um so
here we compared a few different
methods. We are going to learn about
reward models or verifiers on Monday
more but let's take a look at these
examples. So we have a number of samples
and then we are measuring the success
rate here like basically what would be
the output of this system. Um majority
voting or the green one is we we just
see which answer among the generated
answers has um appeared the most. So
based on that we just select that answer
or that response as the output of our
system. Does that make sense? It's just
majority voting. And uh the blue line
here is coverage. This is assuming we
had a perfect selector or verifier in
this case. And as you can see here,
there is a large difference between
majority voting which plateau plateaus
after 10 or 50 samples and what we could
possibly get if we had a perfect
verifier. So this is a very very large
gap. Um especially and this gap is even
more pronounced if you have harder
problems. So for example the math
capital math here data set is a harder
more complex data set than GSM8K
and we here we we compared other methods
like using a reward model and com add
and um that uh generates that measures
gives a reward per answer and we take
the best of best of those or ways to
combine these two we'll learn more about
these reward models basically they're
LLM based
kind of LLMs that are trained to to kind
of um score their the response quality
and even with those there is a large cap
gap. Uh and this is what we call the
generation verification gap. So the
generation it turns out we can generate
a lot of good responses but the
verification is this basically this gap
is tells us how much we can actually
capture those responses or those uh
correct answers.
Um, the reason methods such as majority
voting doesn't work is that as we look
into the quality of answers, it turns
out that for some problems that are
hardest to solve, sometimes we see that
they were solved maybe even once or two
times or three times across the thousand
or 10,000 samples that we take from the
model. So these correct problems um uh
are actually very rarely solved by the
model with the samples that we are
taking from it. So it makes sense that a
majority voting mechanism cannot capture
those because they're rare. But for many
of the problems in this case especially
for the GSM8K which is simpler because
uh the the answers or responses are more
are simpler to generate majority voting
works for many of the problems. But even
even in this case for some of the
hardest problems the frequency of
correct answer is actually pretty low.
So that makes it harder from a
verification perspective. How do you how
do you find them? How do you find out
which ones are correct?
Um, now I want you to here are some
questions that some discuss discussion
questions that I want to put it here for
like something like 2 minutes or so and
I want you to think about it and
hopefully we'll have some volunteers
uh or our I um and volunteer some of you
to answer some of them. So, two minutes
for this.
Maybe we talk after.
>> Okay, let's get back.
Who wants to answer question one?
This I I I I'm very interested in how
you would build on this if you were if
you were to do some research here or or
what what you what uh database you you
got from these papers.
anyone?
>> Yes. Like one takeaway is that uh
sampling many uh answers and can shoot
like if you have a good verifier it
really helps with your
and the second take away is that the the
quality of the verifier is very
important of doing this approach.
>> That's right.
>> Anything else?
Yes.
>> Examples for example [clears throat]
like the model generally the solutions
and the model or each of the solution
that I need to generate a new solution
even if you're not sure the solution is
>> are you talking about revising a
solution
>> uh yeah
>> by next
Yeah.
>> Okay. We're going to hear about it in a
minute.
>> Sounds good. Yes.
>> I'm looking at it in two directions. One
is the science for safe and accuracy.
And for that um I will look at a hybrid
approach where I will develop a
knowledge graph along with a advanced RA
documentation method and then returns to
the RA method when I do the inance time
score is lesser on the accuracy and more
or less rely on the knowledge to give
you more accurate answers. That way you
can increase the speed of the answer
while also maintaining accuracy. So you
were suggesting we use rack to to uh
boost
>> or compare we go with the knowledge
first and then only when um we feel that
the accuracies that are coming have to
come up we go through because rag also
learns the uh time and there is um
>> yeah so you're asking rag can help with
the efficiency in the time find time
domain
>> we're trying to reduce the dependency on
to increase the accuracy
Okay, one more. Maybe you were waiting.
>> Um, yeah. So, I think something that I
thought about also is just um a even if
it's
easy to medium level of difficulty
respect or verification or like
verifiable domains. Um
this it it would be cool to see sort of
how uh past K changes with respect to K
when we kind of employ sort of initial
search techniques like almost like a
self-study approach. if there's some way
to maybe consolidate like let's let the
model explore this domain gather
insights as if you know you're not
asking it to sample any solutions yet
and maybe that can get you know related
to some output context and we can then
follow into parallel sampling and we
might see maybe better trends um with
respect to
>> absolutely
>> and we're going to learn about some of
the ways to improve test time scaling
beyond just repeated sampling
>> um including self-study search and tool
use um maybe one more.
>> Yes.
>> Um well, one interesting might be like
verifiers. Um I think like without a
good verifier, then the best you can do
is exactly as what you showed in the
previous slide usually doesn't work very
well for hard problems. But maybe there
are some hard problems where like it's
hard to identify if an answer is correct
because it's too expensive or doesn't
it's just too hard.
But it's easy to find like an answer is
wrong, right? So you can like project um
like bad answers. Maybe that would be
more obvious in terms of thinking and
then you can just keep like
an evolutionary pattern. So I guess one
interesting direction would be like
trying to look at different domains
where like
right and also maybe verification is not
fully accurate. Maybe it's a bit lost
like they verify it's it own model
because of the simulation. It's like a
physics or like a dynamic simulation,
robotics, something how you would.
>> Yeah, basically there are other ways to
filter out the incorrect answers. Maybe
use a simulation or some
other tool use or another model to do
that depending on the domain. So the all
of the data set here the 10,000
different samples per problem is
available on on on hugging face if
anybody is interested to go around how
to kind of improve like shrink that
generation verification gap. Um that
could be a potentially a good research
project for the for the course. Um yes
last question. Yeah. Could one try to
generate multiple verifiers like maybe
generate 10,000 verifiers and then do a
majority deing like what the result
verifiers?
>> Yes,
that's also a very interesting research
question. So on Monday we're going to
learn about this we work that we've done
on ensembling but like a week supervised
ensembling of verifiers. We don't have a
thousand of them, but we can have 10 or
20 of them. But that direction is
definitely also interesting. It's very
costly though from a compute
perspective. Um maybe we should move on
to the any any other like about the the
other two questions. Anything? Um I
think we discussed some of it in our
discussion but anything that you want to
share last minute? Yes.
to what extent was it investigated
whether the coverage number could be
[clears throat] like engineering task
for example like it could be test cases
but it's actually not
>> yeah for like for example for the math
problems we manually looked into the to
the answered questions and it was
something above like a 90 like 7 8% by
manually checking that but that's also
always a a a case for a failure mode if
your unit tests don't have true coverage
of the code.
>> So the quality of the verifier matters.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Maybe it's more
generating it like trees. So but you're
verifying each note.
>> Yeah. Let's talk about that and what's
coming next and how we can make
uh different ways of uh test time
scaling. So with the monkeys framework
we we we see we saw that repeated
sampling is effective but there are
other ways to uh scale sampling and
let's take a look at this paper uh
scaling LLM test time compute optimally
can be more effective than uh scaling
model parameters. We're going to touch
on certain as aspects of it that is most
relevant to test time scaling. So there
are two way like parallel sampling is
one way for us to generate multiple
answers per input question.
But there is another way to generate or
generate answers or use test time
scaling to improve the quality and that
is when we do sequential revisions. For
example, we the model comes up with one
initial steps of the problem or one
initial approach for solving the problem
and it keeps revising that or it keeps
like improving and adding to that and
that is the sequential approach. So
instead of asking the model multiple
times, we let the model know that it can
keep revising its answers, look into
that from a different angles and um and
continue doing so until it's confident
that it's ready to generate an answer
and then finally output that. Yes.
>> So is this by our own printing or is the
model system?
>> Um in this case, let's let's assume by
our own prompting prompting. But when
you look at the reasoning models, they
are now trained like internally we have
we see this kind of behavior in them. So
they do this um uh revisions uh
sometimes in their own answers. Um now
there is another way to scale test time
compute and that is how much how we
select the answers. So for the parallel
sampling, we we looked into the outcome
like there are n different responses. We
look into the outcome and see if they're
correct or not. We mentioned unit test
and so on. But there's also this other
way of learning base or outcome reward
models where they where they look into
the outcome and and say whether they're
correct or not. Of course, their
accuracy or quality can be limited,
especially if we uh go to new domains,
but outcomebased reward model is another
way that they look into the final answer
and they generate a score. Basically,
these models are trained to um to give a
reward based on an output. Then there is
also the process reward models. So in
the difference between process and
outcome is that process reward models
are designed to give a score per step of
the generated solution. For example, we
have a math problems. There are like
five steps that the model takes before
generating a solution.
outcome reward mo sorry process reward
models again we learn about this more on
Monday I believe um are trained to give
a score for the steps of the generation
so that's the difference between the two
uh now for best of end sampling with a
verifier again the problem is easy we
generate parallel samples and then we
can use an outcomebased reward model um
to to see which one has the highest
score and then take that as um as our
answer.
Then there are um other ways that we can
bring these reward models into the
processing into the into our test time
scaling framework. For example, here
let's assume at each level of this
answering this question, we can take
four s we have a budget of four samples.
uh we take these four samples and then
here use a process reward model or PRM
to to kind of like in this case we
select the top two uh with the highest
score from our PRM. Then again we sample
from them uh and and and and we continue
and we can have a threshold on what how
the to for selecting the top kind of um
two two kind responses in this case and
expanding the tree from there. So here
we are doing a beam search approach to
that uses the process reward model to
guide how we are sampling our model. Is
that clear?
Yes.
>> How do you choose the option
>> based on the PRM score? So the process
reward model is trained to generate a
score imagine between zero and one based
on the a step given given the question
and or or just a step alone
>> is the PR function from the language
model. Yes, PRMs are generally also fine
from a language model. As you can
imagine, they would work better for in
domain kind of types of task. So, if you
have a certain task that you want to uh
a certain benchmark that you want to
optimize for, of course, training a PRM
on a like a subset of that task helps
you with test time scaling on that task
better than across new task. uh but
because they're language model based
they they do exhibit some generalization
across task as well.
>> Yes.
>> For the process reward uh is this a
reward that's being computed in
practice? I don't know what the research
is like per token that is being done or
maybe like blocks of tokens and then
it's being computed.
>> Yeah, it's not per token. is per like
step like imagine and this is something
we're going to learn about in future
lectures. Imagine these are like a math
problem and then there are steps to
answer that like in one way to do it is
to have humans annotate the quality of
each step like yes or no this is good or
bad and then training the model based on
each step which could be like you can
assume it's like one kind of
intellectually meaningful chunk of the
result or it could be you can define it
as a sentence and so on.
And of course um as it's intuitive as
it's very intuitive if you combine the
two of outcomebased reward model and
parallel best of end and sequential
revisions you get better results. this
field is still there's a lot of unknown
kind of uh questions around this and but
combining the two for example one simple
way to kind combine that is um instead
of one parallel one sample and revisions
you do two and and you use your um and
you get to two final answers and then
you use um
the best one either using your PRM or OM
to select how the two the two are, but
you're augmenting each parallel sample
with these sequential revisions and you
can use a PRM to guide that search for
each parallel for each sequential
revision. Um, something that's
interesting is that the PRM
there are many off-the-shelf PRMs that
you can use for your task. So you can go
and say take a pre-trained PRM and use
that to guide the search for your own
task and you can potentially find a PRM
that is most kind of relevant to the
type of task that you're doing and you
want to do test time scaling on or you
can train your own PRM and and OM based
on your own data as well.
Um so this paper looked into the math
data set and uh something like 12k train
set 500 test questions um used a palm
model. And what was interesting here is
that they defined a notion of difficulty
uh for compute opt uh for for measuring
these different scaling behaviors and
for that they looked into the pass at
one performance of the model on each
problem.
Um and and by just measuring that they
define okay these are the problems that
are hard. These are the problems based
on like how many of the generated
answers are correct across a body of a
number of samples. They had like
different like five different bins for
the complexity of the problem and they
did that as we see to kind of get some
conclusion about what test time scaling
works better for harder or easier task.
um they also train their own process
reward model and even they fine-tune a
model for creating these revisions. But
right now the models every model that we
use pretty much it's capable it's just
as long as it's instruction tuned is
capable of doing revisions if you prompt
the model to do so ask the model to do
so. Um and there are some interesting
observations here. Uh for example, here
is the majority voting for these
problems. The accuracy as the generation
budget increases. And then this is the
the the purple one is the OM one. Um and
the green one is the
um PRM one and then the blue one if you
really try to optimize different ways of
mixing and matching things. Um and this
is this area is the one that still is
unopen research like how do we do that?
How do we go about mixing and matching
revisions and uh parallel scaling uh to
optimize the test time scaling because
at the end of the day we want for each
uh accuracy we want the minimum
generation budget to hit that accuracy.
Um and in in a few slides ahead we talk
about one method to optimize this um
scaling and budget um performance per
budget. Um they also looked into these
different bins of difficulty. So number
five is the most difficult questions
because the accuracy is the lowest and
number one and then here on the right
there the these colors is the sequential
to parallel ratio. And while they were
saying that okay in the easier for the
easier problems it seems like this
darkest kind of the darkest purple color
achieves highest accuracy and that's
where we have a lot more sequential kind
of tokens compared to parallel when the
problems are more difficult and to some
extent those are some of the more
interesting problems. This optimality is
kind of harder to say. It's harder to
say whether it's sequential or uh the
the ratio changes even from bucket four
to bucket five on how you how you should
allocate that.
Um another uh observation from this
paper was that um and this is a still
work in progress and I believe still the
true the true observation as of today is
that for easy and medium questions it
seems like additional test time compute
can be more favorable than scaling
pre-training of the model.
So here we have these two like the easy
are the green medium is blue and orange
uh is the hard questions. It seems like
if we look into the ratio of inference
tokens to pre-training tokens uh it's
positive uh uh here but as we get to uh
it's positive for the uh easy and medium
problem but for the hardest problem it
seems like larger models like a more
pre-training or larger models still do
better if you are from a from a tokens
optimized perspective.
And this is something that we we we have
seen in many of our research in the lab
and or around the lab as well. Um it
seems like like models simpler like open
source models or smaller models are
becoming more and more useful as we take
more test time compute apply more test
time compute on them. But still for the
very very hard problem still the
frontier models which presumably use
more pre-training and they're larger
they do better uh even if we had a whole
lot like infinite budget for test time
scaling. Of course we don't have
infinite budget but any reasonably large
test time scale. Yes. Um, in this case,
how are you?
Does it seem like for inverse use it
once like pressure tokens, it's like use
it once and you can use it.
>> Yes, that that is that is true. But in
general from a but this is a still so
basically yes in pre-training is done
once but scaling is every time right
every time we run the model but but
still um
so so so but still this is an
interesting observation from the
perspective of are we done doing
pre-training because we can just keep
sampling from the models we have or no
pre-training is still helpful and we
should do more and more right um not
everyone can pre-train a large model
right so even if pre-training was an
option for u achieving was better than
test time scaling in any scale not
everyone can do that because it's a very
expensive process so this is very
interesting that for many problems we
can do test time scaling even if it's we
do every time for a new problem because
that's feasible. But also on the other
hand, for the hardest problems, we still
need to do pre-training and better
models still do better,
>> right? Um that makes sense. I was just
curious like precisely like in the
middle graph when it says like the ratio
is one of the difference to that or like
what
there's also one is used for a single
task.
>> No, no, it's not it's not exactly that.
It's more like some some ratio of
pre-training to inference compute. It's
not a one to one because it doesn't make
sense in that case, right?
>> For the hard questions part, why is it
that larger models still better?
So, can can you take a smaller model and
yet make it an expert on hard questions?
Yeah, you can always like fine-tune a
model
to become better on a certain set of
questions, but we are talking about a
more general perspective of like let's
have a whole lot of data that's like
general, not specific to a specific task
and just like compare like the the
common recipes that you use for training
models. Let's just follow that and then
see how much they do better at test
time. Um
any other questions?
Okay. Um so here are maybe we discussed
some of these already but here are some
more questions that I give you another
two minutes. Let me check the time. And
yes, we do have time um to think about
this. I think this helps you kind of
like uh absorb some of the the topics
that we that we learned uh or uh heard
about in the previous slides and then we
discuss them in 2 minutes.
Okay. Should we should we start? Anyone
wants to add any comments here or any
questions you might have?
Yes.
>> Um, so do you try sequential and you try
curl? What about tree search? And in
that case, like you're kind of doing
>> you're mixing the both.
>> Yeah. You're kind of mixing, right?
>> Yeah. There's no universal answer that
can be there. But the general sentiment
was that that does better like some sort
of combining the two
>> than doing like you do some kind of like
cleaning and like reduce a lot of the
confuse that you're doing, right? or
like reuse control that you're doing
because it's a tree like yes
[clears throat]
>> that is when we discuss the beam search
stuff and the PRM like bringing a PRM to
kind of cut the uh tree at it at each
level and explore only the more uh
promising branches.
>> Anything else? Yes,
>> we have discussion with it for example
point for you was thinking that
bigger problem the more paths you have
towards the success of solving it
therefore you require it could be more
sequential while with harder problems
you would there's few paths to solving
that you would need many paralle to find
at least one viable solution and we
started thinking a bit also why could
you do this in a chain of thoughts kind
of way where you are doing your chain
fault but verifying throughout the steps
in the uniforms is that pruning and
these branches that are violating
anything.
>> Yeah. So in terms of sequential you're
saying that for easier ones easier
problems the for harder problems you
mean you need more exploration
potentially for easier
>> to the correct answer. Well, for easier
problems
um because like any kind of path might
lead us to the correct answer. We might
not need to explore different parallel
solutions. Yeah, that is an intuitive
kind of way of thinking about this.
Any other thoughts?
Um in general this is a very interesting
appro kind of problem to think about how
do you how do let's assume that this
tokens that you generate is like a knob
that you have to increase problem the
quality of the responses how do you
allocate this knob and how do you elicit
these uh generations from the model so
let's think about like in the following
I'm going to talk about one way to do to
optimize these kind of test time scale
scaling to generate optimized answers
and that is the archon paper um an
architecture research framework for
inference time scaling um uh so the
problem state and your TA is uh one of
the co-authors of this work so the
problem in this paper is that again we
are interesting interested to see um how
we can mix and match different inference
time scaling methods to build a kind of
optimize the frontier of uh capability
or correctness versus cost. Um
and and and the the other thing that um
again all of these questions basically
saying the same thing that how how we
can optimize assigning in press compute
two different task um and basically
design mechanisms that gets us to the
high quality answers while not wasting
too many tokens and generations.
So here is the RQ like in this case we
thought of inference scaling in this uh
project as like an inference
architecture design problem. Um so here
is how this uh the frame archive
framework works on the input side we had
a set of target benchmarks that we
wanted to get good good results on these
benchmarks. So these are the benchmarks
we are optimizing for. There's an
inference called budget and then there's
also a set of available LLMs because we
can always mix and match different
models also to get to and to a correct
answer for a input question. And then we
have a set of inference time techniques
which I'm going to describe in the in
the following slides. And then we have
we designed this optimizer
uh it's called itas. It's inference time
architecture search that basically tells
us how to put together these different
models and different inference time
techniques together whether it's
parallel sampling sequential and all
that in order to uh get high quality
results given the budget the inference
call budget that we have. how to
optimize the quality of results based on
that and then the output is this
architecture that mixes and matches
these different techniques and models
together.
Um so let's take a look at different
inference time operations. So first we
have the gen we called it the generation
but this is basically um
the
the just sampling from the model and
this can be part of the repeated
sampling approach right so if we
generate n we use n generations at a
time that means we have generated n
different responses to our input
question so that's one one type of
inference time scaling another one is
fusion which is surprisingly a very
effective method. So fusion is let's say
we have k um k different responses
and we want to generate one output
response out of these k um fusion takes
an llm and asks an llm the same exact
question that I just said basically it
says here's the input question here are
k different responses to this input
question given all of this generate or
synthes ize one output response for the
input question. Basically, we are
showing all of the K generations to the
model such that the the LLM can generate
an output answer while being aware of
all the possible ways that uh this
question is answered.
Um and this is kind of it goes under the
C category of sequential update, right?
we have this parallel samples but then
we are kind of fusing them into one
answer. Then there is the um um critic
which
basically for any given response we can
ask a model to um
generate or describe the weaknesses or
strengths of these response and that
could be one kind of inference scaling
action. Um and then we have the ranker.
This is again these are all prompting
based optimization for the model. We
don't have we haven't trained the model
to do this specific test time scaling
task. We just ask the model in the
instruction prompt that um can you rank
these generated responses from the
previous step um based on the their
quality.
Um
and then the vifiers generates the
returns the response with while also
talking about the reasoning of how why
it came came to this um kind of way to
score a certain answer. Um I'll get to
the next two uh unit test generation and
evaluation in a bit but just to show you
how effective these different uh
inference time scaling techniques are
let's take a look at this win win win
rate um
um for
what task we don't have the task here
but it's one of the task of like uh one
of these benchmarks that I don't I don't
know if you remember the task.
>> Yeah. Um, so it's some some pro question
answering reasoning benchmark. So here
let's take a look at how these things
work. So uh first we have let's say we
have a number of repeated samples from
the model. Uh it goes from 1 to 10 on
the left side. Let's focus on the graph
on the left side. And then the orange
one is the kind of worst possible way of
approaching. We just randomly select one
and look at the quality and the
correctness of this response. Um the
green one is when we use the model to
rank them to rank the responses and we
select the top one ranked by the model
and and report that that already does
better than uh [clears throat] that
already does better than the the orange
one.
The blue one is um oracle selection
meaning let's assume we are not mixing
these responses in any way. We we just
select the best one generated.
Let's say we have an Oracle verifier
that can tell us which one of these is
correct. And that obviously does better
than just asking the model to rank them
because it's an Oracle verifier. And
then we get to the red one which is
where we when we use the fusion. So
basically for each each point here let's
say we are at five. Uh the red data
point is basically we have given these
five responses to the model and asked
the model to synthesize one answer one
final answer given all this information.
And it's so interesting and this
paradigm is so powerful that that can on
its own improve the quality of responses
over oracle selection.
Um and then finally the purple one is
where we um
instead of fusing
um all the uh all the all the responses
we first selected the top five
um in the and and then and then we went
about fusing them. So it seems like some
sort of a filtering of the two does
better.
Now on the right side we are doing a
different experiment and that is we are
um on the left side we had only one
model generating everything. On the left
side we had we were using we we were
adding models. So first one is just one
model generating one answer. Two the
baseline is two different models
generating one answer and 10 is 10
different models each generating one
answer. And we see that of course the
random result um becomes worse because
the model we looked on the left was I
think it was among the better models in
this ensemble. But we still see the same
trend trend even if these responses are
coming from different models like
basically the same trend of how these uh
all follow each other. Yes. Which model
is like using if you're using like 10
different models you're asking like
somebody else to rank or fuse your
>> uh I think it's the model number one in
this case the same the model that was in
all of those and this was uh kind of the
way we created the ensemble was first
with the best model and then added the
second best model and so on.
Okay. Now let's take a look at a couple
other inference time techniques and that
is unit test generation and evaluation.
I think one of you was were were
mentioning something like this earlier
as well that where we can ask the model
to generate these unit tests say when it
gets to coding task or math optim math
problem solving or other reasoning task
tasks. Um, and the unit test evaluation
is even crazier. Like instead of like
running the unit test, you're asking the
model to evaluate a generated answer uh
against a unit test.
For example, um here is a prompt uh
check for so the coding problem in this
case is check for balancness of round
brackets in an input string. That that's
a coding question. And then here is an
example input. Here is the type of unit
test that the model could generate. Um
for example, given a string with an odd
number of brackets, the solution should
output no, which is like a good unit
test in this case. Uh another one is
when a closing bracket is encountered,
it must match the most recently open
brackets that hasn't been matched yet.
That's another kind of reasonable unit
test. And then you can ask the model to
actually generate the code to test this
as well. Um, now let's take a look at
the types. I don't know if you guys see
this well, but the type, but this is so
big there's no way for me to put it here
with like large font. But this is the
type of architectures that aron found.
So basically now think about it this
way. we have different ways of mixing
and matching models and inference time
techniques and we can define these
layers of optimization. Uh for example,
the first layer in this case is
generation and then these generations
are from different models in this case
and then we have a a critic and a
ranker. So basically the critique will
criticize these generations and then we
rank them and then we the optimizer
found that we could have a bunch of
fusers at this point like each fuses
these gener these responses into one
output um and then we can go from there
um continue this critique ranker. And
this was like a rather complicated
architecture. And the way that we
optimized this architecture is that uh
we did some kind of pre-processing to
reduce the space of uh optimization. For
example, the fact that we found this uh
sequence of generation, critique, ranker
and fuser do really well. We did that
offline. So we limited the search space
just because doing this search is very
expensive. We need to run a lot of
inference calls. But then the way we
optimize it that we had a held out data
set that we could we had a training data
set that we could optimize against that
and create this accuracy versus the
number of calls that we are making to
these models kind of as a as a metric
that we are optimizing against. We want
to maximize accuracy and min for any
given um budget inference budget that we
have.
Um and this is for one some of the
coding problems. This was an optimized
architecture. Basically we generate a
ton of samples. Uh we generate unit
tests and then we evaluate them.
Now
um
an interesting property here is that
we found that stacking more and more
layers of these inference time
techniques or making it deep in a way
actually does help with our
um accuracy.
Um in this case for example the
rightmost pink uh graph is uh where we
have uh where we have an ensemble
meaning we have different models in our
loop and we have three layers of
critique critiques and fusers and a
final fuser fuser layer. Um and this is
like significantly better across many of
these tasks over both just using a
simple the best model only once or the
best model eight times with like one
layer of fusion. So it seems like these
additional layers that we are adding
here is actually just like in deep
learning we are adding layers and
pre-training and the model gets better.
Seems like these careful kind of
addition of these inference layers are
helping the model become more and more
accurate. across many of the tasks. Um
this is true. And so now the optimizer
itself, we used an Beijian optimizer
again to simplify the search space. We
did a few things. Um for example, we
limited the optimizer to only use one
inference time technique per layer. Um
and the first layer was always just the
generator. And then we had this cascade
of ranker, critic, verifier.
Uh they they could go anywhere, but we
we made certain kind of modifications to
the search search space. For example, a
critic should go before a ranker or a
fuser always because we did some testing
locally and saw this is a better choice.
Um and then a unit test generator must
be followed by an evaluator op. Um and
uh we again we use a Beijan optimizer to
do this. Um this is often a very
powerful um method methodology
um uh a a ton of like good open-source
software to do Beijan optimization for
you. Basically you have this search
space that you want to configure it with
different uh different kind of uh
choices for the architecture and the
output side you have the accuracy and
you want to optimize for that. Um and
this does better than greedy search or
random selection. We are much more
sample efficient in terms of number of
configurations that aron searches until
it reaches a final kind of architecture
and we can define different objectives
for it. For example, um available models
uh inference time inference call budget
is are one of them are are some of them.
Um the thing that I want you to uh pay
attention to in this graph is that this
interesting property that archon is at
the end generating one response at the
very end right so it's like you're
optimizing pass at one at the very end
and what was interesting here is that u
while using just the open-source models
we could match or exceed um these closed
source models at the time uh the
frontier co source model at the time by
a large mar mar mar mar mar mar mar mar
mar mar mar mar mar mar mar mar mar mar
mar mar margin across many of these task
in terms of pass at one here's the
average pass at one improvement and not
only that we we could train archon to be
task specific so when we are doing the
Beijan optimizing we only look into a
certain task and we test on that or we
could train archon to be general purpose
so we wanted it to do whether bad good
across many to do well across many tasks
and even that the general purpose one
does really really well and better than
the the frontier models across these
task and that was like a very
interesting observation
um that you can design these inference
time architectures that do well beyond
the task or uh the limited task that
they're trained of. So on average in
this case we were outperforming GPT40 or
COD 3.5 sonnet in pass one uh by an
average of 14.1%
across these uh instruction following
reasoning and math and coding problems.
Uh here are some questions but um that I
want you to think think about but since
we're out of time um hopefully you think
about it uh yourself and
hope you have a happy weekend.